NADEEM HAQUE, P.ENG.

1190 McCraney Street East
Oakville, Ontario
Canada
L6H 4S5
Tel: (905) 842-4379
haque nadeem@hotmail.com

EDUCATION

1981 – 1985 King's College, University of London, U.K.

B.Sc. (Eng.) in Civil Engineering.

1978 – 1981 University of Toronto

B.A. in Economics.

SUMMARY

Civil Engineer with extensive and in-depth experience in Asset Management (buildings (including Housing), water/sewer/storm water/equipment/fleet/solid waste management, roads etc.), building sciences, structural engineering, and environmental site assessments. Projects have involved condition assessments of buildings (including parking garages and balconies), capital planning (SOGR), technical review of buildings to comply with codes, structural design, structural analysis, project management, site inspections, writing engineering and asset management plan reports and studies, RFPs, RFQs, asset management research, proposals, implementing and developing engineering and asset management software, software training, and technical research. Member of the Professional Engineers Ontario (PEO).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

July, 2017 to March 22, 2019 (Contract) Regional Municipality of York

Asset Management Project Engineer

- Project Engineer in the Community and Health Services (CHS) Department, Housing Services Branch, Infrastructure Asset Management Group. The Housing Services Branch owns and manages Social Housing facilities in York Region.
- Wrote the entire Request for Proposal (RFP) on the CHS Asset Management Plan; I was the Project Manager/Engineer for this project. The CHS Asset Management Plan final draft was completed in March, 2019 and included Proposed Levels of Service, far in advance of the Regulatory 2024 deadline for non-core assets.
- Finalized the Building Condition Assessment and Energy Audit RFP; I was the Project Manager/Engineer for the project for both Housing York Inc. (HYI) and independent Housing Provider facilities, all of which were successfully assessed.
- Lead for the CHS Department for the Corporate Asset Management Plan (the first of its kind for York Region) this has been completed. This project involved co-ordinating and analyzing data from Paramedics and Seniors Services, in addition to Housing York Inc. (HYI) facilities.
- Managing Valuations of all York Region Social Housing Facilities using the reconstruction method.

- Developed the State of the Infrastructure Report (2017) Lead for the CHS Department (ongoing).
- Developed 10 Year Capital Plans for HYI facilities and for non-HYI Housing Providers' facilities.
- Performed Operational Reviews (technical part) of non-HYI Housing Providers' buildings/facilities.
- As Project Manager, co-ordinating the various stakeholders on the project; ensuring deadlines are being met and arranging site visits for the Consultant for Building Condition Assessments and Energy Audits; meeting with Consultants (for the condition assessment and the asset management plan projects) on a regular basis. As Lead for CHS, holding meetings with the Corporate Coordinating Committee for Asset Management, and the Consultant, to develop the CHS portion of the State of the Infrastructure Report (2017). Made a presentation to the Corporate Coordinating Committee for Asset Management concerning Community and Health Services. Reviewing various reports being developed by the Consultants for QA /QC and technical and explanatory content.
- Prepared RFQs for valuation of York Region social housing facilities and managed the project (assets are worth almost \$1 billion).
- Contract Management.
- Other technical research as required in Building Sciences or Energy Conservation.

July, 2015 to October 2015 Contract &/ January, 2016 to May 2017 Cole Engineering Group, Markham

Asset Management Consultant (Project Manager)

Conducted project management, report writing, workshops and research for the following projects:

- Project Manager for York Region Solid Waste Management Asset Management Plan (State of the Infrastructure, Levels of Service/Risk Assessment, Asset Management Strategy, Data Strategy, Financial Strategy (100 Year Capital Plan), Asset Management Collaboration and Continuous Improvement (Road Map)). Recommended Asset Management replacement costs (a Technical Report was prepared and added to the Asset Management Plan). This plan was successfully completed and the results were used in York Region's Corporate Asset Management Plan.
- Uxbridge (Durham Region) Water Pollution Control Plant Condition Assessment. Managed all engineering disciplines (electrical, structural, civil, process mechanical and building mechanical) and in charge of the final report as Assistant Project Manager.
- Newmarket Asset Management Strategy: best practices and determination of Asset Management Maturity through meetings with all departments that were part of the strategy; this was conducted with the Cole Asset Management Team and the Prime Consultant.

Proposal Writing

• Extensive proposal writing for Asset Management RFPs/Rosters.

Structural Engineer

• Structural analysis and design for wood residential buildings (new home models being built): from roof (trusses) to foundation, submitted by various Architects for the engineer's stamp/building permit.

November, 2010 to June, 2015 Infrastructure Solutions (Engineering) Inc., Mississauga Vice President of Engineering Services/Project Manager

- Developed Asset Management Plans (AMPs) for over sixty municipalities in Ontario. The asset types included: water network, sewer network, buildings, bridges, culverts, fleet, equipment, etc. This also required managing a team of professionals with experience in finance and engineering as project managers. Producing an AMP required following several key steps, from project initialization to closure:
 - o Uploading asset data into Municipal DataWorks.
 - o Determining the State of the Infrastructure (SOTI/SOIR).
 - o Specifying Levels of Service.
 - o Generating the Capital Plan.
 - o Preparing Financial Projections.
 - o Executive Summary.
- Extensive technical analysis of the assets was performed for the AMPs, including:
 - o Capital planning for roads; supervision and report writing for Road Needs Studies to determine condition ratings.
 - o OSIM (Ontario Structure Inspection Manual bridge and culvert inspection manual) data entry to determine condition ratings by Municipal DataWorks software.
 - o Developing degradation curves for sewerlines, waterlines, roads, bridges and culverts.
 - o Determining/obtaining replacement costs.
 - o Developing strategies/triggers for rehabilitation/replacement/reconstruction.
 - o Development of in-house applications for roads and Capital Plans.
 - o Reviewing Building Assessment field reports to incorporate into the AMP.
 - o Technical research on both linear and non-linear assets.
 - o Conducting webinar training sessions for software and on client sites and also training Infrastructure Solutions Inc. staff on the software.
 - o Preparing PSAB (Public Sector Accounting Board) reports for tangible capital asset.
 - o Participating in writing, reviewing and editing/finalizing the AMP.

April 2009 to November 2009

KML Building Solutions/Genesis Inc.

Senior Structural Design Engineer and Design Manager

- Responsible for the design of buildings using primarily cold-formed steel and red steel.
- Involved in the design of the following structures:
 - o Applefest Lodge (residential); sunpod solar panels (for California); foundation and superstructure for Assisted (Special Services) Housing in Brampton; modular buildings for TTC office expansion and other clients; Amico Seasons Senior Residence Ontario's first over seven-storey cold-formed steel structure.
- Resolving structural issues for projects currently being built; site work; checking drawings; managing designers.

March 2007 to March 2009

Mitek Canada Inc.

Structural Design Engineer

- Sealing Engineer for Ontario roof and floor trusses for residential, commercial, institutional and farm buildings submitted by the fabricators and their engineers using Mitek 20/20 software.
- Structural analysis, re-design if required, repair/redesign of broken, damaged or improperly installed trusses.

- Analyzing roof placement plans for the entire building (i.e. the interconnection between all trusses on the building to see if loads were being transferred properly etc.).
- Designing for snow loading/drift and updating standard details; using a suite of graphics programs connected to Mitek 20/20, for structural design and drafting.

October 2006 to January 2007 Amvic Building System

Technical Writer for Structural Engineering Product

Contract

 Wrote and illustrated almost the entire technical and installation manual for the major new structural engineering product: the "AmDeck Floor and Roof System" which is an innovative insulated concrete form. The manual can be viewed at www.amvicsystem.com

August, 2001 – June, 2002 Datawire Communication Networks Inc., Mississauga Software Design Contract

• Designed and developed an in-house work management software system to handle internal and external customer service for the first of its kind virtual transaction processing network, Datawire's revolutionary 'VXN'.

November, 1997 – April, 2001 PricewaterhouseCoopers (PwC), Toronto Consultant in the Physical Asset Management Practice (PAM)

Project included:

- Nortel Networks Global Procurement project:
 - o MS Access Database Reports' development for strategic sourcing; RFP research; RFI preparation and management.
- Implementation of Computerized Maintenance Management Systems:
- Proposal writing for Facilities and Maintenance Management projects
- Prepared CMMS and Facilities Management methodologies.
- Statistical/graphical summaries of Maintenance Self-Assessment data.
- Benchmarking, including a major electrical and instrumentation management benchmarking report for Suncor Energy Inc., helping the client win a national award for plant maintenance management.

1994 – 1997 Peto MacCallum Ltd., Toronto/Protech Building Inspections, Toronto Project Engineer

- Investigations in building science projects and structural rehabilitation surveys; concrete test analysis/reporting; floor flatness calculations; pull-tests for concrete; report writing; Site engineer for the entire Novopharm building construction rebar inspections. (Peto MacCallum).
- Phase 1 and 2 Environmental Site Assessments and building inspections. (Protech).

1991 – 1994 **Project Engineer**

Junior/Intermediate Environmental Engineer and Civil Engineer Soil Probe Ltd./Shaheen and Peaker Ltd.

- Several Phase 1 Environmental Site Assessments (ESA). (Shaheen and Peaker)
- Decommissioning of Canadian Forces Base, Downsview (Phase 3); site Engineer for Hydrocarbon Removal; Phase 2 ESA for the City of Toronto. (Shaheen and Peaker)
- Site engineer for new subdivisions (engineered fill supervision and compaction testing for roads). (Soil Probe).

1986–1990 Robert Halsall and Associates Ltd., Toronto/Stone and Webster Canada/Trow Inc. (now EXP) Junior Engineer

- Condition surveys/reports of underground parking garages and high-rise/commercial buildings; structural rehabilitation inspection/investigations; contract administration; feasibility reports. (Robert Halsall).
- 1986 with Stone and Webster Canada, Structural Engineering Assistant for a pipe-support system for a power station; 1987 as Junior Engineer at Trow Inc., Consulting Engineers, in concrete admixture design/testing.